Guide to the Loy Connell Smith and Eunice Andrews Smith Bland Papers, 1958-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Loy Connell Smith and Eunice Andrews Smith Bland papers 1958-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bland, Eunice Andrews Smith, 1928-
2.5 linear feet Extent: 1875 Items
Dr. Loy Connell Smith (1925-1968) and his wife, Eunice Andrews Smith (b. 1928), were Southern Baptist missionaries to Nigeria from 1959 through 1968. Collection includes family correspondence, photographs, hospital publications, and audiovisual material from the Smith family's time as missionaries in Nigeria. Contains information about the death of Dr. Loy Connell Smith in a car accident and the Smith family's subsequent return to the United States.
RL.10009
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
RESTRICTED: Box 2 is closed to researchers until 2022. Box 3 contains original audiovisual materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Loy Connell Smith and Eunice Andrews Smith Bland Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Biographical and Historical Note
Loy Connell Smith (b. 1925) and Eunice Andrews Smith (b. 1928) were originally from North Carolina and married in 1949. They were appointed as missionaries to Nigeria by the Southern Baptist Foreign Missions Board in 1958, and after a year of seminary, moved to Ogbomosho, Nigeria, where they worked in medicine. Dr. L.C. Smith worked as a staff physician at the Baptist Hospital, while Eunice Smith taught nursing and worked in the mission's medical laboratory. The couple had three children.
On May 16, 1968, a car accident in Nigeria killed Dr. L.C. Smith and severely injured Eunice. The family buried him in Ogbomosho. In August, Eunice and the children returned to the United States where she worked at the Foreign Mission Board's Africa Office. She married Dr. Thomas A. Bland in 1979. Dr. Bland died in 2010.
Collection Overview
Collection includes family correspondence, photographs, audiovisual tapes and reels, and materials collected by the Smiths regarding their work at the Baptist Hospital. Correspondence has been sorted chronologically by year. Letters between Eunice Andrews Smith and her mother, Annie Wells Andrews, are restricted for 10 years (until 2022). More information about the history of the family can be found in the biographical and background files in Box 1.
The collection also contains a significant amount of information surrounding the Smiths' car accident and Dr. L.C. Smith's death in 1968. Materials on this event include correspondence, records and films of his funeral and memorial services, and materials about memorial funds and plaques in honor of Dr. Smith's service.
Subject Headings
Bland, Eunice Andrews Smith, 1928-; Smith, Loy Connell, 1925-1968; Southern Baptist Convention. Foreign Mission Board; Nigeria -- History -- 20th century; Baptists -- Missions -- Nigeria; Missions -- Nigeria -- History; Missions -- Africa; Married people in missionary work -- Africa
Related Material
This collection is part of a larger group of Southern Baptist Missionaries in Nigeria. Related collections include the Pool Family Papers, the McGee Family Papers, and the Roberson Family Papers.
Contents of Collection
- Smith Family Materials, (3 boxes)
  Box 2 of this collection is closed to research until 2022. Box 3 is restricted because it contains audiovisual materials; these are closed until use copies can be made.
  - Collection Outline and Information (Box 1)
  - Loy Connell Smith and Eunice Andrews Smith timelines and narratives (Box 1)
  - Appointment as Foreign Missionaries, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Holiday letters to family and friends, 1959-1972 (Box 1)
  - Connell's letters to family, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1959-1967, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1968 (before accident) (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1968 (after accident) (Box 1)
  - Death of Loy Connell Smith, 1968-1969, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Ogbomosho Baptist Hospital materials, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Return to the United States, 1968 (Box 1)
  - L.C. Smith Memorial Fund, Nigerian Baptist Convention, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
  - L.C. Smith Memorial Fund, Foreign Mission Board, 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - Death of Dr. Emanuel Dahunsi, 20 Jan. 1979 (Box 1)
  - L.C. Smith medical certificates (photocopies), 1948-1962 (Box 1)
  - Plaque for L.C. Smith at Ogbomosho Baptist Hospital, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Plaque for L.C. Smith at Bowman Gray School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, N.C., 1971 (Box 1)
  - L.C. Smith Memorial Chapel, Chalybeate Springs Baptist Church, N.C., 1969 (Box 1)
  - Eunice's trip to Nigeria, 5th anniversary memorial service, 1973 (Box 1)
  - 50th Anniversary of Ogbomosho Hospital, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Melba Smith's trip to Nigeria, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Death of Loy Connell Smith Jr., 1995 (Box 1)
  - Loy Connell Smith, Jr. Memorial Fund, Baptist Medical Center, Nigeria, 1995-1999 (Box 1)
  - L.C. Smith's publications in medical journals, 1955-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1960 and 1963 (Box 1)
  - Family photographs, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Letters from Eunice Andrews Smith to her mother, Annie Wells Andrews, 1959-1968, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    CLOSED: This material is closed to research until 2022.
  - Audiovisual Materials (Box 3)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Tape letter from Mrs. L.C. Smith to Mrs. D.B. Andrews (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from L.C. Smith to Mrs. D.B. Andrews, Nigerian music, drumming and singing (Box 3)
    - Tape letter to Rev. T.S. Smith (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from Mrs. L.C. Smith to Mr. Truman Smith, Christmas (tape 1) (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from Mrs. L.C. Smith to Mr. Truman Smith, Christmas (tape 2) (Box 3)
    - Tape letter to Mr. Truman Smith (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from L.C. Smith to Mrs. Truman Smith, Nov. 17, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from Dr. L.C. Smith to Mr. Truman Smith, Aug. 8, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Tape letter from Dr. L.C. Smith to Mrs. Truman Smith, Oct. 1963 (Box 3)
    - Funeral and burial taken by TV station for local news, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Memorial service, Ogbomosho, May 28, 1973; widow Eunice Smith, present (Box 3)
    - Memorial service, Ogbomosho, Melba Smith present, unveiling of headstones of Dr. L.C. Smith and Alice Miller (Box 3)
    - Smith memorial service (Box 3)
    - Final service (with commentary) in memory of Dr. L.C. Smith (Box 3)
    - 4 untitled reels (Box 3)